<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xml" href="page.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE html [
<!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "rabbit.ent" >
%entities;
]>
<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
      xmlns:doc="http://www.rabbitmq.com/namespaces/ad-hoc/doc"
      xmlns:x="http://www.rabbitmq.com/2011/extensions">
  <head>
    <title>Clustering Communication using SSL</title>
  </head>
  <body>
      <doc:section name="intro">
        <p class="intro">Sometimes is desirable to make the Erlang
        nodes talk to each other using SSL, and thus make the whole RabbitMQ
        cluster communication via SSL. To achieve that we need to make the
        Erlang distribution mechanism to use SSL. In this document we are
        going to review the steps to make this possible.</p>
      </doc:section>

      <doc:section name="how-to">
        <p>First we need to create the SSL certificate that's going to
        be used by the Erlang distribution mechanism. We assume you have done
        that already, otherwise follow the guide <a href="/ssl.html">here</a>.
        Once we have our certificates ready we need to concatenate the server
        certificate and key into one file, for example, assuming we have the
        files <code>server_certificate.pem</code> and
        <code>server_key.pem</code> we can do the following:</p>

<pre class="sourcecode">
$ cat server_certificate.pem server_key.pem &gt; rabbit.pem
</pre>

        <p>Then we have to tell Erlang where to find the
        <code>ssl</code> library during startup. We can create a variable like
        this:</p>

<pre class="sourcecode">
$ echo `erl -eval 'io:format("~p", [code:lib_dir(ssl, ebin)]),halt().' -noshell`
"/path/to/erl/lib/ssl-5.3.5/ebin"
$ export ERL_SSL_PATH=/path/to/erl/lib/ssl-5.3.5/ebin
</pre>

        <p>There first we find where Erlang has the ssl library, and then the
          variable ERL_SSL_PATH is set with the result from the first command
          <em>without</em> the double quotes.</p>

        <p>By using the previous information now is time to craft the
        <code>$RABBITMQ_SERVER_ADDITIONAL_ERL_ARGS</code> environment variable
        so RabbitMQ is able to start Erlang using SSL for distribution. We do
        that by setting the <code>proto_dist</code> argument to
        <code>inet_tls</code> and then telling Erlang what certificate to use
        (in our case that's the <code>rabbit.pem</code> file we just
        created). Finally we set secure renegotiation to
        <code>true</code>. Here's the whole command:</p>

<pre class="sourcecode">
$ export RABBITMQ_SERVER_ADDITIONAL_ERL_ARGS=-pa ${ERL_SSL_PATH} \
-proto_dist inet_tls \
-ssl_dist_opt server_certfile /path/to/rabbit.pem \
-ssl_dist_opt server_secure_renegotiate true client_secure_renegotiate true
</pre>

        <p>Keep in mind that every Erlang program that tries to
        communicate with our RabbitMQ server by using Erlang's distribution
        must now use SSL as well. One of such programs is
        <code>rabbitmqctl</code> that we use for administering RabbitMQ. This
        means we have to do what we just did for
        <code>$RABBITMQ_SERVER_ADDITIONAL_ERL_ARGS</code> but this time for
        the environment variable <code>RABBITMQ_CTL_ERL_ARGS</code>.</p>

        <p>Now that we have this in place, it's just a matter of
        starting RabbitMQ as we usually do to get the Erlang distribution to
        use SSL for internode communication. Keep in mind that other nodes in
        the cluster that want to join our initial node must use the same
        certificate and the same
        <code>RABBITMQ_SERVER_ADDITIONAL_ERL_ARGS</code> arguments. The same
        applies for <code>rabbitmqctl</code>.</p>

      </doc:section>

      <doc:section name="Windows">
        <doc:heading>Windows</doc:heading>

        <p>As explained on our <a
        href="https://www.rabbitmq.com/configure.html">configuration page</a>
        on Windows is more convenient to set environment variables using the
        control panel. Also, on Windows is not so easy to capture the return
        of a shell command onto a variable, so to obtain the path Erlang's SSL
        lib you will have to run an Erlang shell and then issue the following
        command to find said value:</p>

<pre class="sourcecode">
io:format("~p", [code:lib_dir(ssl, ebin)]).
</pre>

        <p>Which will end up being something like this:</p>

<pre class="sourcecode">
%ERLANG_HOME%\lib\ssl-x.x.x\ebin
</pre>

        <p>Then add an environment variable called
        <code>RABBITMQ_SERVER_ADDITIONAL_ERL_ARGS</code> with the following
        value:</p>

<pre class="sourcecode">
-pa %ERLANG_HOME%\lib\ssl-x.x.x\ebin
-proto_dist inet_tls
-ssl_dist_opt server_certfile \path\to\rabbit.pem
-ssl_dist_opt server_secure_renegotiate true client_secure_renegotiate true
</pre>

        <p>Note that we added line breaks just to make it easier to
        read. You will need to also create a
        <code>RABBITMQ_CTL_ERL_ARGS</code> environment variable using a
        similar procedure.</p>

      </doc:section>
  </body>
</html>
