<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xml" href="page.xsl"?>
<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
      xmlns:doc="http://www.rabbitmq.com/namespaces/ad-hoc/doc"
      xmlns:x="http://www.rabbitmq.com/2011/extensions">
  <head>
    <title>Confirms (aka Publisher Acknowledgements)</title>
  </head>
  <body>
    <p>
      Using standard AMQP 0-9-1, the only way to guarantee that a
      message isn't lost is by using transactions -- make the
      channel transactional, publish the message, commit.  In this
      case, transactions are unnecessarily heavyweight and
      decrease throughput by a factor of 250.  To remedy this,
      a confirmation mechanism was introduced.
    </p>

    <p>
      To enable confirms, a client sends the
      <code>confirm.select</code> method.  Depending on whether
      <code>no-wait</code> was set or not, the broker may respond
      with a <code>confirm.select-ok</code>.  Once the
      <code>confirm.select</code> method is used on a channel, it
      is said to be in confirm mode.  A transactional channel
      cannot be put into confirm mode and once a channel is in
      confirm mode, it cannot be made transactional.
    </p>

    <p>
      Once a channel is in confirm mode, both the broker and the
      client count messages (counting starts at 1 on the first
      <code>confirm.select</code>).  The broker then confirms
      messages as it handles them by sending a
      <code>basic.ack</code> on the same channel. The
      <code>delivery-tag</code> field contains the sequence number
      of the confirmed message.  The broker may also set the
      <code>multiple</code> field in <code>basic.ack</code> to
      indicate that all messages up to and including the one with
      the sequence number have been handled.
    </p>

    <p>
      An example in Java that publishes a large number of
      messages to a channel in confirm mode and waits for the
      acknowledgements can be found <a
                                       href="http://hg.rabbitmq.com/rabbitmq-java-client/file/default/test/src/com/rabbitmq/examples/ConfirmDontLoseMessages.java">here</a>.
    </p>

    <h3>Negative Acknowledgment</h3>
    <p>
      In exceptional cases when the broker is unable to handle
      messages successfully, instead of a <code>basic.ack</code>,
      the broker will send a <code>basic.nack</code>.  In this
      context, fields of the <code>basic.nack</code> have the same
      meaning as the corresponding ones in <code>basic.ack</code>
      and the <code>requeue</code> field should be ignored.  By
      nack'ing one or more messages, the broker indicates that it
      was unable to process the messages and refuses responsibility
      for them; at that point, the client may choose to re-publish
      the messages.
    </p>

    <p>
      After a channel is put into confirm mode, all subsequently
      published messages will be confirmed or nack'd once.  No
      guarantees are made as to how soon a message is confirmed.
      No message will be both confirmed and nack'd.
    </p>

    <p>
      <code>basic.nack</code> will only be delivered if an internal
      error occurs in the Erlang process responsible for a queue.
    </p>

    <h3 id="when">When will messages be confirmed?</h3>

    <p>
      For unroutable messages, the broker will issue a confirm
      once the exchange verifies a message won't route to any queue
      (returns an empty list of queues). If the message is also
      published as mandatory, the <code>basic.return</code> is sent
      to the client before <code>basic.ack</code>.
    </p>

    <p>
      For routable messages, the <code>basic.ack</code> is sent when a
      message has been accepted by all the queues. For persistent
      messages routed to durable queues, this <strong>means persisting
      to disk</strong>. For mirrored queues, this means that all
      mirrors have accepted the message.
    </p>

    <h3 id="latency">Ack Latency for Persistent Messages</h3>
    <p>
      <code>basic.ack</code> for a persistent message routed to a
      durable queue will be sent after persisting the message to
      disk. The RabbitMQ message store persists messages to disk in
      batches after an interval (a few hundred milliseconds) to
      minimise the number of fsync(2) calls, or when a queue is idle.

      This means that under a constant load, latency for
      <code>basic.ack</code> can reach a few hundred milliseconds. To
      improve throughput, applications are strongly advised to
      process acknowledgements asynchronously (as a stream) or publish
      batches of messages and wait for outstanding confirms. The exact
      API for this varies between client libraries.
    </p>

    <h3>Confirms and Guaranteed Delivery</h3>

    <p>
      The broker loses persistent messages if it crashes before
      said messages are written to disk.  Under certain
      conditions, this causes the broker to behave in surprising
      ways.
    </p>

    <p>
      For instance, consider this scenario:
      <ol>
        <li>a client publishes a persistent message to a durable
          queue</li>
        <li>a client consumes the message from the queue (noting
          that the message is persistent and the queue
          durable), but doesn't yet ack it,</li>
        <li>the broker dies and is restarted, and</li>
        <li>the client reconnects and starts consuming messages.</li>
      </ol>
      At this point, the client could reasonably assume that the
      message will be delivered again.  This is not the case: the
      restart has caused the broker to lose the message.  In order to
      guarantee persistence, a client should use confirms.  If the
      publisher's channel had been in confirm mode, the publisher
      would <em>not</em> have received an ack for the lost message
      (since the message hadn't been written to disk yet).
    </p>
  </body>
</html>
