<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xml" href="page.xsl"?>
<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
      xmlns:doc="http://www.rabbitmq.com/namespaces/ad-hoc/doc"
      xmlns:x="http://www.rabbitmq.com/2011/extensions">
  <head>
    <title>Dead Letter Exchanges</title>
  </head>
  <body>
    <p>
      Messages from a queue can be 'dead-lettered'; that is, republished to
      another exchange when any of the following events occur:
      <ul>
        <li>The message is rejected (<code>basic.reject</code> or
          <code>basic.nack</code>) with <code>requeue=false</code>,</li>
        <li>The TTL for the message expires; or</li>
        <li>The queue length limit is exceeded.</li>
      </ul>
    </p>

    <p>
      Dead letter exchanges (DLXs) are normal exchanges.  They can be
      any of the usual types and are declared as usual.
    </p>

    <p>
      For any given queue, a DLX can be defined by clients using the
      queue's arguments, or in the server
      using <a href="parameters.html#policies">policies</a>. In the
      case where both policy and arguments specify a DLX, the one
      specified in arguments overrules the one specified in policy.
    </p>

    <doc:section>
      <doc:heading>Configuration using arguments</doc:heading>
      <p>
        To set the dead letter exchange for a queue, set
        the <code>x-dead-letter-exchange</code> argument to the
        name of the exchange:
      </p>

      <pre class="sourcecode">
channel.exchangeDeclare("some.exchange.name", "direct");

Map&lt;String, Object&gt; args = new HashMap&lt;String, Object&gt;();
args.put("x-dead-letter-exchange", "some.exchange.name");
channel.queueDeclare("myqueue", false, false, false, args);</pre>

      <p>
        The code above declares a new exchange called
        <code>some.exchange.name</code> and sets this new exchange
        as the dead letter exchange for a newly created queue.
        Note that the exchange does not have to be declared when
        the queue is declared, but it should exist by the time
        messages need to be dead-lettered; if it is missing then,
        the messages will be silently dropped.
      </p>

      <p>
        You may also specify a routing key to be used when
        dead-lettering messages.  If this is not set, the
        message's own routing keys will be used.
        <pre class="sourcecode">
args.put("x-dead-letter-routing-key", "some-routing-key");</pre>
      </p>

      <p>
        When a dead letter exchange has been specified, in addition to
        the usual configure permissions on the declared queue, the user
        needs to have read permissions on that queue and write
        permissions on the dead letter exchange. Permissions are
        verified at the time of queue declaration.
      </p>
    </doc:section>

    <doc:section>
      <doc:heading>Configuration using policy</doc:heading>

      <p>
        To specify a DLX using policy, add the key "dead-letter-exchange"
        to a policy definition. For example:
      </p>

      <table>
        <tr>
          <th>rabbitmqctl</th>
          <td>
            <pre>rabbitmqctl set_policy DLX ".*" '{"dead-letter-exchange":"my-dlx"}' --apply-to queues</pre>
          </td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <th>rabbitmqctl (Windows)</th>
          <td>
            <pre>rabbitmqctl set_policy DLX ".*" "{""dead-letter-exchange"":""my-dlx""}" --apply-to queues</pre>
          </td>
        </tr>
      </table>

      <p>
        This applies the DLX "my-dlx" to all queues.
      </p>

      <p>
        Similarly, an explicit routing key can be specified by adding
        the key "dead-letter-routing-key" to the policy.
      </p>

      <p>
        Policies can also be defined using the management plugin, see
        the <a href="parameters.html#policies">policy
        documentation</a> for more details.
      </p>
    </doc:section>

    <doc:section>
      <doc:heading>Routing Dead-Lettered Messages</doc:heading>
      <p>
        Dead-lettered messages are routed to their dead letter
        exchange either:
        <ul>
          <li>with the routing key specified for the queue they
            were on; or, <em>if this was not set</em>,</li>
          <li>with the same routing keys they were originally
            published with.</li>
        </ul>
      </p>
      <p>
        For example, if you publish a message to an exchange with
        routing key <code>foo</code>, and that message is
        dead-lettered, it will be published to its dead letter
        exchange with routing key <code>foo</code>.  If the queue
        the message originally landed on had been declared with
        <code>x-dead-letter-routing-key</code> set to
        <code>bar</code>, then the message will be published to
        its dead letter exchange with routing key
        <code>bar</code>.
      </p>
      <p>
        Note that, if a specific routing key was not set for the
        queue, messages on it are dead-lettered with <em>all</em>
        their original routing keys.  This includes routing keys
        added by the <code>CC</code> and <code>BCC</code> headers
        (see <a href="sender-selected.html">Sender-selected
          distribution</a> for details on these two headers).
      </p>
      <p>
        Dead-lettered messages are re-published with publisher
        confirms turned on internally so, the dead-letter queues
        the messages eventually land on must confirm the messages
        before they are removed from the original queue.  In other
        words, the publishing queue will <em>not</em> remove
        messages before the dead-letter queues acknowledge
        receiving them (see <a href="confirms.html">Confirms</a> for
        details on the guarantees made).  Note that, in the event
        of an unclean broker shutdown, the same message may be
        duplicated on both the original queue and on the
        dead-letter queues.
      </p>
      <p>
        It is possible to form a cycle of dead-letter queues.  For
        instance, this can happen when a queue dead-letters
        messages to the default exchange without specifiying a
        dead-letter routing key.  Messages in such cycles (i.e.
        messages that reach the same queue twice) will be
        dropped <em>if the entire cycle is due to message expiry</em>.
      </p>
    </doc:section>
    <doc:section>
      <doc:heading>Dead-Lettered Messages</doc:heading>
      <p>
        Dead-lettering a message modifies its headers:
        <ul>
          <li>the exchange name is replaced with that of the
            latest dead-letter exchange,</li>
          <li>the routing key may be replaced with that specified
            in a dead letter queue,</li>
          <li>if the above happens, the <code>CC</code> header
            will also be removed, and</li>
          <li>the <code>BCC</code> header will be removed as per
            <a href="sender-selected.html">Sender-selected
              distribution</a>.</li>
        </ul>
      </p>
      <p>
        The dead-lettering process adds an array to the header of
        each dead-lettered message named <code>x-death</code>.
        This array contains an entry for each time the message was
        dead-lettered.  Each such entry is a table that consists
        of several fields:
        <ul>
          <li><code>queue</code> - the name of the queue the
            message was in before it was dead-lettered,</li>
          <li><code>reason</code> - see below,</li>
          <li><code>time</code> - the date and time the message
            was dead lettered as a 64-bit AMQP format timestamp,</li>
          <li><code>exchange</code> - the exchange the message was
            published to (note that this will be a dead letter
            exchange if the message is dead lettered multiple
            times), and</li>
          <li><code>routing-keys</code> - the routing keys
            (including <code>CC</code> keys but excluding
            <code>BCC</code> ones) the message was published
            with.</li>
          <li><code>original-expiration</code> (if the message was
            dead-letterered due to <a
            href="ttl.html#per-message-ttl">per-message TTL</a>) - the
            original <code>expiration</code> property of the message.
            The <code>expiration</code> property is removed from the
            message on dead-lettering in order to prevent it from
            expiring again in any queues it is routed to.</li>
        </ul>
      </p>
      <p>
        The <code>reason</code> is a name describing why the
        message was dead-lettered and is one of the following:

        <ul>
          <li><code>rejected</code> - the message was rejected
            with <code>requeue=false</code>,</li>
          <li><code>expired</code> - the TTL of the message
            expired; or</li>
          <li><code>maxlen</code> - the maximum allowed queue
            length was exceeded.</li>
        </ul>
      </p>
      <p>
        Note that the array is sorted most-recent-first, so the
        most recent dead-lettering will be recorded in the first
        entry.
      </p>
    </doc:section>
  </body>
</html>
