<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xml" href="page.xsl"?>
<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
      xmlns:doc="http://www.rabbitmq.com/namespaces/ad-hoc/doc"
      xmlns:x="http://www.rabbitmq.com/2011/extensions">
  <head>
    <title>Heartbeats</title>
  </head>
  <body>
    <doc:section name="overview">
      <doc:heading>Detecting Dead TCP Connections with Heartbeats</doc:heading>
      <p>
        In some types of network failure, packet loss can mean that
        disrupted TCP connections take a moderately long time (about 11
        minutes with default configuration on Linux, for example) to be
        detected by the operating system. AMQP 0-9-1 offers a
        <i>heartbeat</i> feature to ensure that the application layer
        promptly finds out about disrupted connections (and also
        completely unresponsive peers). Heartbeats also defend against
        certain network equipment which may terminate "idle" TCP
        connections.
      </p>
    </doc:section>


    <doc:section name="heartbeats-timeout">
      <doc:heading>Heartbeat Timeout Interval</doc:heading>
      <p>
        The heartbeat timeout value defines after what period of time
        peer TCP connection should be considered dead by RabbitMQ and
        client libraries. This value is negotiated between the client
        and RabbitMQ server at the time of connection.he client must
        be configured to request heartbeats. In RabbitMQ versions 3.0
        and higher, the broker will attempt to negotiate heartbeats by
        default (although the client can still veto them). The timeout
        is in seconds.
      </p>
      <p>
        Heartbeat frames are sent about every <code>timeout / 2</code> seconds.
        After two missed heartbeats, the peer is considered to be unreachable.
        Different clients manifest this differently but TCP connection will
        be closed. When a client detects that RabbitMQ node is unreachable due to
        a heartbeat, it needs to re-connect.
      </p>
      <p>
        Heartbeats can be disabled by setting timeout interval to <code>0</code>.
      </p>
    </doc:section>

    <doc:section name="using-heartbeats-in-java">
      <doc:heading>Enabling Heartbeats with Java Client</doc:heading>
      <p>
        To configure heartbeat timeout in the Java client, set it with
        <code>ConnectionFactory#setRequestedHeartbeat</code> before
        creating a connection:
      </p>

<pre class="sourcecode">
ConnectionFactory cf = new ConnectionFactory();

// set heartbeat timeout to 60 seconds
cf.setRequestedHeartbeat(60);
</pre>
    </doc:section>

    <doc:section name="using-heartbeats-in-dotnet">
      <doc:heading>Enabling Heartbeats with the .NET Client</doc:heading>
      <p>
        To configure heartbeat timeout in the .NET client, set it with
        <code>ConnectionFactory.RequestedHeartbeat</code> before
        creating a connection:
      </p>

<pre class="sourcecode">
var cf = new ConnectionFactory();

// set heartbeat timeout to 60 seconds
cf.RequestedHeartbeat = 60;
</pre>
    </doc:section>
  </body>
</html>
