<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xml" href="page.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE html [
<!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "rabbit.ent" >
%entities;
]>
<!--
Copyright (c) 2007-2016 Pivotal Software, Inc.

All rights reserved. This program and the accompanying materials
are made available under the terms of the under the Apache License,
Version 2.0 (the "License”); you may not use this file except in compliance
with the License. You may obtain a copy of the License at

http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
limitations under the License.
-->

<html  xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xmlns:doc="http://www.rabbitmq.com/namespaces/ad-hoc/doc">
  <head>
    <title>Java Tools</title>
  </head>
  <body>
    <p class="intro">
      This page documents some Java-based utility programs (PerfTest, Tracer).
    </p>

    <doc:section name="throughput-load-testing">
      <doc:heading>PerfTest</doc:heading>
      <p>
        RabbitMQ has a basic throughput testing tool, PerfTest (docs, source
        code and releases), that is based on the Java client and can be
        configured to simulate basic workloads. PerfTest has extra tools
        that produce HTML graphs of the output.

        A RabbitMQ cluster can be limited by a number of factors, from
        infrastructure-level constraints (e.g. network bandwidth) to
        RabbitMQ configuration and topology to applications that
        publish and consume. PerfTest can demonstrate baseline
        performance of a node or a cluster of nodes.
      </p>

      <doc:subsection name="perf-test-installation">
        <doc:heading>Installation</doc:heading>

        <p>
          PerfTest is distributed as a <a href="https://github.com/rabbitmq/rabbitmq-perf-test/releases">binary build archive</a> as well as
          <a href="http://search.maven.org/#search%7Cga%7C1%7Ca%3A%22perf-test%22">Maven</a> (the latter allows it to be
          also used as a library).
        </p>

        <p>
          The distribution contains a script (<code>bin/runjava</code> or <code>bin/runjava.bat</code>)
          to run Java with the class path correctly configured, e.g.
          <code>bin/runjava com.rabbitmq.perf.PerfTest</code> runs
          the <code>PerfTest</code> Java class.
        </p>
        <p>
          To verify a PerfTest installation, use

          <pre class="sourcecode bash">bin/runjava com.rabbitmq.perf.PerfTest --help</pre>
        </p>
      </doc:subsection>

      <doc:subsection name="using-perf-test">
        <doc:heading>Using PerfTest</doc:heading>
        <p>
          The most basic way of running PerfTest only specifies a URI to
          connect to, a number of publishers to use (say, 1) and a
          number of consumers to use (say, 2). Note that RabbitMQ Java
          client can achieve high rates for publishing (up to 80 to 90K
          messages/second), given enough bandwidth and some safety
          measures (publisher confirms) enabled, so overprovisioning
          publishers is rarely necessary for a basic test.

          The following command runs PerfTest with a single publisher
          without publisher confirms, two consumers (each receiving a
          copy of every message) that use automatic acknowledgement mode
          and a single queue named “throughput-test-x1-y2”. Publishers
          will publish as quickly as possible, without any rate
          limiting. Results will be prefixed with “test 1” for easier
          identification and comparison:

<pre class="sourcecode bash">
bin/runjava com.rabbitmq.perf.PerfTest -x 1 -y 2 -u "throughput-test-1" -a --id “test 1”
</pre>
        </p>

        <p>
          This modification will use 2 publishers and 4 consumers,
          typically yielding higher throughput given enough CPU cores
          on the machine and RabbitMQ nodes:

<pre class="sourcecode bash">
bin/runjava com.rabbitmq.perf.PerfTest -x 2 -y 4 -u "throughput-test-2" -a --id “test 2”
</pre>
        </p>

        <p>
          This modification switches consumers to manual acknowledgements:

<pre class="sourcecode bash">
bin/runjava com.rabbitmq.perf.PerfTest -x 1 -y 2 -u "throughput-test-3" --id “test 3”
</pre>
        </p>

        <p>
          This modification changes message size from default (1 kB) to 4 kB:

<pre class="sourcecode bash">
bin/runjava com.rabbitmq.perf.PerfTest -x 1 -y 2 -u "throughput-test-4" --id “test 4” -s 4000
</pre>
        </p>

        <p>
          PerfTest can use durable queues and persistent messages:

<pre class="sourcecode bash">
bin/runjava com.rabbitmq.perf.PerfTest -x 1 -y 2 -u "throughput-test-5" --id "test-5" -f persistent
</pre>
        </p>

        <p>
          When PerfTest is running, it is important to monitor various
          publisher and consumer metrics provided by the <a href="/management.html">management
          UI</a>. For example, it is possible to see how much network
          bandwidth a publisher has been using recently on the
          connection page.
        </p>

        <p>
          Queue page demonstrates message rates, consumer count,
          acknowledgement mode used by the consumers, consumer
          utilisation and message location break down (disk, RAM,
          paged out transient messages, etc). When durable queues and
          persistent messages are used, node I/O and message
          store/queue index operation metrics become particularly
          important to monitor.
        </p>

        <p>
          Consumers can ack multiple messages at once, for example, 100 in this configuration:

<pre class="sourcecode bash">
bin/runjava com.rabbitmq.perf.PerfTest -x 1 -y 2 -u "throughput-test-6" --id "test-6" -f persistent --multiAckEvery 100
</pre>
        </p>

        <p>
<a href="/confirms.html">Consumer prefetch (QoS)</a> can be configured as well (in this example to 500):

<pre class="sourcecode bash">
bin/runjava com.rabbitmq.perf.PerfTest -x 1 -y 2 -u "throughput-test-7" --id "test-7" -f persistent --multiAckEvery 200 -q 500
</pre>
        </p>

        <p>
          Publisher confirms can be used with maximum of N outstanding publishes:

<pre class="sourcecode bash">
bin/runjava com.rabbitmq.perf.PerfTest -x 1 -y 2 -u "throughput-test-8" --id "test-8" -f persistent -q 500 -c 500
</pre>
        </p>

        <p>
          PerfTest can publish only a certain number of messages instead of running until shut down:

<pre class="sourcecode bash">
bin/runjava com.rabbitmq.perf.PerfTest -x 1 -y 2 -u "throughput-test-10" --id "test-10" -f persistent -q 500 -pmessages 100000
</pre>
        </p>

        <p>
          Publisher rate can be limited:

<pre class="sourcecode bash">
bin/runjava com.rabbitmq.perf.PerfTest -x 1 -y 2 -u "throughput-test-11" --id "test-11" -f persistent -q 500 --rate 5000
</pre>
        </p>

        <p>
          Consumer rate can be limited as well to simulate slower consumers or create a backlog:

<pre class="sourcecode bash">
bin/runjava com.rabbitmq.perf.PerfTest -x 1 -y 2 -u "throughput-test-12" --id "test-12" -f persistent --rate 5000 --consumerRate 2000
</pre>
        </p>

        <p>
          PerfTest can be configured to run for a limited amount of time (in seconds):

<pre class="sourcecode bash">
bin/runjava com.rabbitmq.perf.PerfTest -x 1 -y 2 -u "throughput-test-13" --id "test-13" -f persistent -z 30
</pre>

          Note that the consumer rate limit is applied per consumer, so in the
          configuration above the limit is actually 2 * 2000 = 4000
          deliveries/second.

        </p>

        <p>
          Running PerfTest without consumers and with a limited number
          of messages can be used to pre-populate a queue, e.g. with
          1M messages 1 kB in size each::

<pre class="sourcecode bash">
bin/runjava com.rabbitmq.perf.PerfTest -y0 -p -u “”throughput-test-14” -s 1000 -C 1000000 --id “test-14” -f persistent
</pre>
        </p>

        <p>
          To consume from a pre-declared and pre-populated queue without starting any publishers,
          use

<pre class="sourcecode bash">
bin/runjava com.rabbitmq.perf.PerfTest -x0 -y10 -p -u “”throughput-test-14” --id “test-15”
</pre>
        </p>

        <p>
          PerfTest is useful for establishing baseline cluster throughput with
          various configurations but does not simulate many other aspects of
          real world applications. It is also biased towards very simplistic
          workloads that use a single queue, which provides <a href="/queues.html">limited CPU utilisation</a> on RabbitMQ nodes and
          is not recommended for most cases.

          Multiple PerfTest instances running simultaneously can be used to
          simulate more realistic workloads.
        </p>
      </doc:subsection>


      <doc:subsection name="how-perftest-works">
        <doc:heading>How It Works</doc:heading>

        <p>
          If a queue name is defined (<code>-u "queue-name"</code>),
          PerfTest will create a queue with this name and all
          consumers will consume from this queue. The queue will be
          bound to the direct exchange with its name as the routing
          key. The routing key will be used by producers to send
          messages.  This will cause messages from all producers to be
          sent to this single queue and all consumers to receive
          messages from this single queue.
        </p>
        <p>
          If the queue name is not defined, PerfTest will create a
          random UUID routing key with which producers will publish
          messages.  Each consumer will create its own anonymous queue
          and bind it to the direct exchange with this routing key.
          This will cause each message from all producers to be
          replicated to multiple queues (number of queues equals
          number of consumers), while each consumer will be receiving
          messages from only one queue.
        </p>
      </doc:subsection>


      <doc:subsection name="perf-html">
        <doc:heading>PerfTest Results in HTML</doc:heading>
        <p>
          The <code>PerfTest HTML extension</code> are a set of tools
          that can help you run automated benchmarks by wrapping around the
          <code>PerfTest</code> benchmarking framework. You can provide
          benchmark specs, and the tool will take care of running the benchmark,
          collecting results and displaying them in an HTML page. Learn more
          <a href="https://github.com/rabbitmq/rabbitmq-perf-test/blob/master/html/README.md">here</a>.
        </p>
      </doc:subsection>


    </doc:section>

    <doc:section name="tracer">
      <doc:heading>Tracer</doc:heading>
      <p>
        The tracer is a very basic, very simple AMQP 0-9-1 protocol analyzer, similar in
        purpose to <a href="/amqp-wireshark.html">Wireshark</a>.
        Use it with
        the <code>runtracer</code> or <code>runtracer.bat</code> script:
      </p>
      <pre>runtracer <i>listenPort</i> <i>connectHost</i> <i>connectPort</i></pre>
      <dl>
        <dt>listenPort</dt>
        <dd>port to listen for incoming AMQP connections on - defaults to 5673.</dd>
        <dt>connectHost</dt>
        <dd>hostname to use when making an outbound connection in response to an incoming connection - defaults to localhost.</dd>
        <dt>connectPort</dt>
        <dd>port number to use when making an outbound connection - defaults to 5672.</dd>
      </dl>

      <doc:subsection name="tracer-download">
        <doc:heading>Download and source code</doc:heading>
        <p>
          <a href="https://github.com/rabbitmq/rabbitmq-tracer/releases">Releases</a>
        </p>
        <p>
          <a href="https://github.com/rabbitmq/rabbitmq-tracer">Source code</a>
        </p>
      </doc:subsection>

    </doc:section>
  </body>
</html>
