<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xml" href="page.xsl"?>
<html xmlns:doc="http://www.rabbitmq.com/namespaces/ad-hoc/doc">
  <head>
    <title>RabbitMQ - MacPorts</title>
  </head>
  <body>
    <doc:div>
      <p class="intro">
        This page describes how to install the RabbitMQ server under
        Mac OS X using <a href="http://macports.org/">MacPorts</a>.
      </p>

      <p>
        MacPorts is an easy-to-use system for installing open-source
        software onto Mac OS X computers.  The MacPorts community has
        packaged thousands of projects as <em>ports</em>, including
        the RabbitMQ server.  So once you have <a
        href="http://www.macports.org/install.php">installed
        MacPorts</a>, installing the RabbitMQ server takes just a
        single command:
      </p>
      
      <pre class="sourcecode">sudo port install rabbitmq-server</pre>
      
      <p>See the <a href="http://macports.org/">MacPorts website</a>
      for more information about MacPorts.</p>
    </doc:div>
    
    <doc:section name="repo">
      <doc:heading>
        Using the rabbitmq.com ports repository to install the latest
        server release
      </doc:heading>
      
      <p>
        When a new version of the RabbitMQ server is released, it can
        take some time for the version included in the main collection
        of MacPorts packages to be updated.  So we provide a
        special-purpose MacPorts repository to give OS X users easy
        access to the very latest release of the RabbitMQ server.
      </p>
      
      <p>
        Once you have installed MacPorts, enable the rabbitmq.com
        repository as follows:
      </p>
      
      <ol>
        <li>Open <code>/opt/local/etc/macports/sources.conf</code>
        in a text editor, and add the following <code>http:</code> URL
        before the existing <code>rsync:</code> URL like so:
        
        <pre class="sourcecode">http://www.rabbitmq.com/releases/macports
rsync://rsync.macports.org/release/ports/ [default]</pre>

        <li>Use the following command to cause MacPorts to retrieve
        the package indices from the newly-added repository:

        <pre class="sourcecode">sudo port sync</pre>
        
        <li>If the rabbitmq.com repository has a newer version of
        the RabbitMQ server than the main MacPorts one, this should
        now be visible when in the results of the <code>port
        search</code> command:

        <pre class="sourcecode">sudo port search rabbitmq-server</pre>

        <p>Which, for example, might produce:</p>

        <pre class="sourcecode">rabbitmq-server @1.7.0 (net)
    The RabbitMQ AMQP Server

rabbitmq-server @1.7.1 (net)
    The RabbitMQ AMQP Server

Found 2 ports.</pre>

        <li>You can now install the latest release of
        <code>rabbitmq-server</code> with the command:
       
        <pre class="sourcecode">sudo port install rabbitmq-server</pre>
      </ol>
    </doc:section>
  </body>
</html>
