<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xml" href="page.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE html PUBLIC "bug in xslt processor requires fake doctype"
"otherwise css isn't included" [
<!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "rabbit.ent" >
%entities;
]>
<html xmlns:doc="http://www.rabbitmq.com/namespaces/ad-hoc/doc">
  <head>
    <title>RabbitMQ - Management Plugin</title>
  </head>
  <body>
    <doc:div>
      <p class="intro">
        This is the documentation for the rabbitmq-management
        plugin. The plugin provides an HTTP-based API for management
        and monitoring of your RabbitMQ server, along with a
        browser-based UI.
      </p>

      <doc:toc class="compact">
        <doc:heading>Table of Contents</doc:heading>
      </doc:toc>

      <doc:section name="installation">
        <doc:heading>Installation</doc:heading>
        <p>
          The simplest way to obtain the management plugin is to
          download the binary packages from
          the <a href="plugins.html">plugins page</a> and copy them to
          your plugins directory. See
          the <a href="plugins.html">plugins page</a> for more
          details.
        </p>
        <p>
          If you wish to build the plugin from source, it can be built
          like any other. See
          the <a href="plugin-development.html">plugin development</a>
          page or
          the <a href="http://hg.rabbitmq.com/rabbitmq-management/file/&version-server-hg;/BUILDING">BUILDING</a>
          file for more information.
        </p>
      </doc:section>

      <doc:section name="caveats">
        <doc:heading>Caveats and warnings</doc:heading>
        <p>
          The management plugin is still at an early stage of
          development. Some day this section will be removed, but
          until then you should be aware of the following limitations:
        </p>
        <ul>
          <li>
            <b>Permissions are only enforced sporadically.</b> If a
            user can authenticate with the HTTP API, they can do
            anything.
          </li>
          <li>
            Installing the management plugin will turn on
            fine-grained statistics in the server. <b>This can slow a
            CPU-bound server by 5-10%</b>.
          </li>
          <li>
            All sorts of other features may be missing or buggy. See
            the <a href="http://hg.rabbitmq.com/rabbitmq-management/file/&version-server-hg;/TODO">TODO</a>
            file for more information.
          </li>
        </ul>
      </doc:section>

      <doc:section name="management-ui">
        <doc:heading>Management UI</doc:heading>
        <p>
          After installation, point your browser at
          http://<i>server-name</i>:55672/mgmt/. You will need to
          authenticate as a RabbitMQ user (on a fresh installation the
          user "guest" is created with password "guest"). From here
          you can manage exchanges, queues, bindings, virtual hosts,
          users and permissions. Hopefully the UI is fairly
          self-explanatory.
        </p>
        <p>
          The management UI is implemented as a single static HTML
          page which makes background queries to the HTTP API. As such
          it makes heavy use of Javascript. It has been tested with
          recent versions of Firefox, Chromium and Safari, and with
          versions of Microsoft Internet Explorer back to 6.0. Lynx
          users should use the HTTP API directly.
        </p>
      </doc:section>

      <doc:section name="http-api">
        <doc:heading>HTTP API</doc:heading>
        <p>
          The management plugin will create an HTTP-based API at
          http://<i>server-name</i>:55672/api/. Browse to that
          location for more information on the API. For convenience
          the documentation can also be obtained
          from <a href="http://hg.rabbitmq.com/rabbitmq-management/raw-file/&version-server-hg;/priv/www-api/help.html">our
          Mercurial server</a>.
        </p>
      </doc:section>
    </doc:div>
  </body>
</html>
