<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xml" href="page.xsl"?>
<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xmlns:doc="http://www.rabbitmq.com/namespaces/ad-hoc/doc">
  <head>
    <title>RabbitMQ - Partners</title>
  </head>
  <body>
    <doc:div>    
    
    <h2>Partners and Alliances</h2>
    
    <p>If your company operates a partner model and feel that we may benefit through 
    working together we would love to hear from you.</p>
    <p>We are developing a RabbitMQ Partner Programme of our own for consultancies and 
    system integrators wishing to act as resellers of our product.</p>
    <p>For more information, please <a href="contact.html">get in touch</a>.</p>
  
    <ul class="partners">
      <li id="canonical">
	<h3><a href="http://www.canonical.com/">Canonical Ltd</a></h3>
	<p>
	  Canonical, the commercial sponsor of Ubuntu, is a global
	  organization headquartered in Europe committed to the
	  development, distribution, and support of open source
	  software products and communities. World class
	  commercial support for Ubuntu is available through
	  Canonical's Global Support Services team and partners.
	  Since its launch in October 2004 Ubuntu has become
	  one of the most highly regarded Linux distributions, with
	  millions of users around the world.
	</p>
      </li>
      <li id="microsoft">
	<h3><a href="http://interopvendoralliance.org/">Interop Vendors Alliance</a></h3>
	<p>
	  The Interop Vendor Alliance is a community of software
	  and hardware vendors, founded by Microsoft, working
	  together to enhance interoperability with Microsoft
	  systems.
	</p>
	<p>
	  “Rabbit is a leader in open source and a welcome addition to
	  the IVA family.", said Jas Sandhu, IVA manager, Microsoft. “We
	  are excited about working with Rabbit to promote best
	  practices for interoperability in mixed infrastructure
	  environments and to deliver robust solutions that benefit our
	  mutual customers.”
	</p>
	<p>
	  Microsoft is a trademark or registered trademark of Microsoft
	  Corporation in the United States and other countries.
	</p>
      </li>
      <li id="vmware">
	<h3><a href="http://www.vmware.com/">VMware</a></h3>
	<p>
	  VMware delivers solutions for business infrastructure
	  virtualization that enable IT organizations to energize
	  businesses of all sizes. With the industry leading
	  virtualization platform -- VMware vSphere(TM) --
	  customers rely on VMware to reduce capital and
	  operating expenses, improve agility, ensure business
	  continuity, strengthen security and go green. VMware is
	  the leader in virtualization which consistently ranks as a
	  top priority among CIOs. VMware is headquartered in
	  Silicon Valley with offices throughout the world and can
	  be found online at www.vmware.com. 
	</p>
      </li>
      <li id="kaazing">
	<h3><a href="http://www.kaazing.com/">Kaazing Corporation</a></h3>
	<p>
	  Kaazing's vision is to deliver the best real-time
	  experience for the Internet. Kaazing provides real-time
	  software solutions to customers who really care about
	  their scalability and performance, and end-user
	  experience.
	</p>
	<p>
	  Kaazing's addition of AMQP to the suite of protocols
	  supported by KEG gives developers a new option. By
	  connecting Rich Internet Applications directly to
	  an AMQP message feed, companies can build fast, real-
	  time Web applications without the usual headaches or
	  high costs.
	</p>
      </li>      
      <li id="novell">
	<h3><a href="http://www.novell.com/">Novell, Inc.</a></h3>
	<p>Novell engages in the design, development, maintenance, implementation, 
	and support of open source software for use in business solutions. It provides 
	security and identity management, resource management, desktop, workgroup, 
	and data center solutions on various operating systems, including Linux, 
	NetWare, Windows, and Unix. The company offers identity-driven computing 
	solutions that help customers with their identity management, resource 
	management, and security issues; and Linux and platform services solutions 
	that offer open cross-platform approach to networking and collaboration 
	services, including file, print, messaging, scheduling, and workspace.</p>

	<p><a href="http://www.novell.com/partnerguide/product/211478.html">RabbitMQ at novell.com</a></p>
      </li>      
      <li id="terracotta">
	<h3><a href="http://www.terracotta.com/">Terracotta, Inc.</a></h3>
	<p>Terracotta is infrastructure software that provides affordable and scalable 
	high availability for Java applications. Companies use Terracotta to offload
	work from databases and application servers and to reduce their development 
	efforts. Founded in 2003, Terracotta, Inc. is a private firm headquartered in 
	San Francisco. </p>

	<p><a href="http://www.terracotta.com/">More information is available at http://www.terracotta.org/.</a></p>
      </li>  
    </ul>
    
    </doc:div>
  </body>
</html>
