<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xml" href="page.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE html [
<!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "rabbit.ent" >
%entities;
<!ENTITY metronome_repo "https://github.com/rabbitmq/rabbitmq-metronome/blob/master">
]>
<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
      xmlns:doc="http://www.rabbitmq.com/namespaces/ad-hoc/doc"
      xmlns:x="http://www.rabbitmq.com/2011/extensions">
  <head>
    <title>Plugin Development Guide</title>
  </head>
  <body show-in-this-page="true">
      <p class="intro">
        This is the RabbitMQ Server Plugin Development Guide. It is expected that
        before reading this guide, the reader has a basic understanding of the RabbitMQ
        plugin mechanism. Readers are also expected to have a basic
        understanding of Erlang OTP
        <a href="http://www.erlang.org/doc/system_principles/users_guide.html">system</a> and
        <a href="http://www.erlang.org/doc/design_principles/users_guide.html">design</a> principles.
      </p>

      <doc:section name="why">
        <doc:heading>Why Write A Plugin?</doc:heading>

        <p>
          Writing a RabbitMQ plugin provides a number of appealing possibilities:
        </p>
        <ul>
          <li>
            Enable your application to access internal RabbitMQ functionality that is not exposed
            via the AMQP interface.
          </li>
          <li>
            Running in the same Erlang VM as the broker may increase performance for certain applications.
          </li>
          <li>
            Plugins provide an easy deployment model, since they allow for a single &quot;RabbitMQ Appliance&quot;
            to be built that acts in a self-contained manner. This can be useful both for easing production
            deployments, and for producing all-in-one infrastructure for use during development.
          </li>
        </ul>
      </doc:section>

      <doc:section name="why-not">
        <doc:heading>Why To Not Write A Plugin</doc:heading>

        <p>
          As with any plugin mechanism, consideration should be given when developing functionality as to whether
          embedding it as a plugin is the most appropriate path to take. Some reasons that you might not want to
          develop your functionality as a plugin:
        </p>

        <ul>
          <li>
            Depending on undocumented internal Rabbit APIs can result in your application requiring changes when
            RabbitMQ is updated. If you can do what you need to do without using RabbitMQ internals, then your
            application will be far more compatible in the future.
          </li>
          <li>
            As mentioned in the Admin Guide, a poorly written plugin can result in the entire broker crashing!
          </li>
        </ul>
      </doc:section>

      <doc:section name="getting-started">
        <doc:heading>Getting Started</doc:heading>

        <p>
          To develop a RabbitMQ plugin, a working RabbitMQ development environment
          first needs to be configured. An &quot;umbrella&quot; project is now
          provided to assist in assembling all the necessary repositories. The following
          steps will walk through the process of checking out and using a copy of the
          umbrella project in your local environment.
        </p>
        <ul>
          <li>
            Ensure that you have a working installation of <a href="http://git-scm.com/">Git</a>.
          </li>
          <li>
            Ensure that the dependencies detailed in the <a href="build-server.html#prerequisites">Server Build</a>
            documentation are installed and functional.
          </li>
          <li>
            Clone the RabbitMQ public umbrella:
            <pre class="sourcecode">$ git clone https://github.com/rabbitmq/rabbitmq-public-umbrella.git</pre>
          </li>
          <li>
            Checkout the sub-projects into the Umbrella:
            <pre class="sourcecode">$ cd rabbitmq-public-umbrella
$ make co</pre>
          </li>
          <li>
            Optionally, switch to a different branch, e.g. if you want to build plugins for a particular version of RabbitMQ:
            <pre class="sourcecode">$ make BRANCH=<i>&lt;tag></i> up_c</pre>
          </li>
          <li>
            Ensure that the umbrella environment is functional by building one of the supplied sub-projects, for example <code>rabbitmq-stomp</code>:
            <pre class="sourcecode">$ cd rabbitmq-stomp
$ make</pre>
            This should build the dependencies of STOMP (in this case, this includes the <code>rabbitmq-server</code> sub-project) and then the STOMP adapter.
            You could also run the STOMP tests (issue <code>make test</code> in the sub-project directory), which should all PASS.
          </li>
        </ul>
      </doc:section>

      <doc:section name="installing-plugins-during-development">
        <doc:heading>Activating Plugins During Development</doc:heading>

        <p>
          Instead of requiring that developers rebuild plugin archives and re-install them each time a change
          is made, plugins can be operated in a development-style mode to make it possible to develop plugins
          in place.
        </p>
        <p>
          To enable and activate a plugin in a development environment, create a
          symlink to the build output location of the plugin directory
          from the rabbitmq-server/plugins directory (which you will
          have to create if it does not exist already). For example,
          to enable a development build of the rabbitmq-shovel
          plugin and its dependencies:

          <pre class="sourcecode">$ mkdir -p rabbitmq-server/plugins
$ cd rabbitmq-server/plugins
$ ln -s ../../rabbitmq-erlang-client
$ ln -s ../../rabbitmq-shovel
$ ../scripts/rabbitmq-plugins enable rabbitmq_shovel</pre>
          The plugin will be activated immediately.
        </p>
        <p>
          Conversely, to deactivate a plugin, simply remove the symlink,
          and <code>rabbitmq-plugins disable plugin-name</code>.
        </p>
      </doc:section>

      <doc:section name="plugin-quality-tips">
        <doc:heading>Plugin Quality Tips</doc:heading>

        <p>
          As highlighted in the Administration Guide, badly-written plugins can pose a risk to the stability of the
          broker. The following tips aim to provide a series of best-practices for ensuring that your plugin
          can safely co-exist with Rabbit.
        </p>

        <ul>
          <li>
            Always install a Supervisor above your application. You should never start your application directly,
            instead opting to create a (possibly quite trivial) supervisor that will prevent the Erlang VM from
            shutting down due to a crashed top-level application.
          </li>
        </ul>
      </doc:section>

      <doc:section name="plugin-hello-world">
        <doc:heading>Example Plugin: Metronome</doc:heading>

        <p>
          Seeing as no development guide would be complete without a Hello World example, the following tries to
          provide the basics of how your would build your very own RabbitMQ plugin. The following example details
          how you might build a simple plugin that acts like a metronome. Every second, it fires a message that has
          a routing key in the form yyyy.MM.dd.dow.hh.mm.ss to a topic exchange called &quot;metronome&quot;. Applications
          can attach queues to this exchange with various routing keys in order to be invoked at regular intervals. For
          example, to receive a message every second, a binding of &quot;*.*.*.*.*.*.*&quot; could be applied. To recieve
          a message every minute, a binding of &quot;*.*.*.*.*.*.00&quot; could be applied instead.
        </p>
        <p>
          The <a href="https://github.com/rabbitmq/rabbitmq-metronome">rabbitmq-metronome</a> repository on GitHub
          contains a copy of the code for this plugin. This will be checked out for you in the <code>make
            co</code> step above, or you can check it out separately.
        </p>
        <p>
          The following table should explain the purpose of the various files in the repository.
        </p>
        <table>
          <tr>
            <th>Filename</th>
            <th>Purpose</th>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td><a href="&metronome_repo;/Makefile"><code>Makefile</code></a></td>
            <td>
              The top-level umbrella.mk file aims to make your application's Makefile as declarative as possible. Your
              plugin's Makefile is still a real Makefile however, so you can still do any kind of normal Make tasks.
            </td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td><a href="&metronome_repo;/package.mk"><code>package.mk</code></a></td>
            <td>
              Contains various settings used by the umbrella Makefile.
            </td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td><a href="&metronome_repo;/src/rabbitmq_metronome.app.src"><code>src/rabbitmq_metronome.app.src</code></a></td>
            <td>
              This file declares the dependencies required by the plugin (<code>rabbit</code>
              and <code>amqp_client</code>). These will be available and started before starting the plugin. Note that the real app file is generated from this; there is no need to fill in the list of modules.
            </td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td><a href="&metronome_repo;/src/rabbit_metronome.erl"><code>src/rabbit_metronome.erl</code></a></td>
            <td>
              Implementation of the Erlang "application" behaviour. Provides a means for the Erlang VM to start and
              stop the plugin.
            </td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td><a href="&metronome_repo;/src/rabbit_metronome_sup.erl"><code>src/rabbit_metronome_sup.erl</code></a></td>
            <td>
              Implementation of the Erlang "supervisor" behaviour. Monitors the worker process and restarts it if
              it crashes.
            </td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td><a href="&metronome_repo;/src/rabbit_metronome_worker.erl"><code>src/rabbit_metronome_worker.erl</code></a></td>
            <td>
              The core of the plugin. The worker will connect internally to the broker, then create a task that
              will be triggered every second.
            </td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td><a href="&metronome_repo;/test/src/rabbit_metronome_tests.erl"><code>test/rabbit_metronome_tests.erl</code></a></td>
            <td>
              Automated tests for the plugin.
            </td>
          </tr>
        </table>

        <ul>
          <li>
            Run make to build your application:
            <pre class="sourcecode">$ make</pre>
            Note that the umbrella build system will build the server and the Erlang client first if necessary.
          </li>
          <li>
            Next, associate your plugin (and its dependencies) with the server:
            <pre class="sourcecode">$ mkdir -p rabbitmq-server/plugins
$ cd ../rabbitmq-server/plugins
$ ln -s ../../rabbitmq-erlang-client
$ ln -s ../../rabbitmq-metronome
$ ../scripts/rabbitmq-plugins --offline enable rabbitmq_metronome
$ cd ..</pre>
          </li>
          <li>
            Start up your Rabbit broker:
            <pre class="sourcecode">$ make run</pre>
          </li>
          <li>
            To ensure that your new plugin is up and running, run the following command:
            <pre class="sourcecode">./scripts/rabbitmqctl status</pre>
            If your plugin has loaded successfully, you should see an entry in the returned list that looks
            like: <pre class="sourcecode">{rabbitmq_metronome,"Embedded Rabbit Metronome","0.01"}</pre>
          </li>
          <li>
            You can run the automated tests by issuing:
            <pre class="sourcecode">$ make test</pre>
          </li>
          <li>
            Finally, you can produce a <code>.ez</code> file, suitable for distribution with:
            <pre class="sourcecode">$ make dist</pre>
          </li>
        </ul>
      </doc:section>
  </body>
</html>
