<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xml" href="page.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE html [
<!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "rabbit.ent" >
%entities;
]>
<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
      xmlns:doc="http://www.rabbitmq.com/namespaces/ad-hoc/doc"
      xmlns:x="http://www.rabbitmq.com/2011/extensions">
  <head>
    <title>Priority Queue Support</title>
  </head>
  <body>
    <p>
      RabbitMQ has priority queue implementation in the core as of version <code>3.5.0</code>.
    </p>
    <p>
      You can declare priority queues using the
      <code>x-max-priority</code> argument. This argument should be an integer
      indicating the maximum priority the queue should support. For example,
      using the Java client:
    </p>

    <pre class="code">    Channel ch = ...;
    Map&lt;String, Object&gt; args = new HashMap&lt;String, Object&gt;();
    args.put("x-max-priority", 10);
    ch.queueDeclare("my-priority-queue", true, false, false, args);</pre>

    <p>
      You can then publish prioritised messages using the
      <code>priority</code> field of
      <code>basic.properties</code>. Larger numbers indicate higher
      priority.
    </p>

    <p>
      Because the on-disk format for a priority queue is different,
      <b>priority queues can only be defined by arguments</b>, not
      policies. Queues can never change the number of priorities they
      support.
    </p>

    <h2>Behaviour</h2>

    <p>
      The AMQP 0-9-1 spec is a bit vague about how priorities work. It says
      that all queues MUST support at least 2 priorities, and MAY
      support up to 10. It does not define how messages without a
      priority property are treated.
    </p>

    <p>
      In contrast to the AMQP 0-9-1 spec, RabbitMQ queues by default do not
      support priorities. When creating priority queues, you can
      specify as many priority levels as you like. Note that:
    </p>

    <ul>
      <li>
        There is some in-memory and on-disk cost per priority level
        per queue. There is also an additional CPU cost, especially
        when consuming, so you may not wish to create huge numbers of
        levels.
      </li>
      <li>
        The message <code>priority</code> field is defined as an
        unsigned byte, so in practice priorities should be between 0
        and 255.
      </li>
    </ul>

    <p>
      Messages without a <code>priority</code> property are treated as
      if their priority were 0. Messages with a priority which is
      higher than the queue's maximum are treated as if they were
      published with the maximum priority.
    </p>

    <h2>Interaction with consumers</h2>

    <p>
      It's important to understand how consumers work when working
      with priority queues. By default, consumers may be sent a large
      number of messages before they acknowledge any, limited only by
      network backpressure.
    </p>

    <p>
      So if such a hungry consumer connects to an empty queue to which
      messages are subsequently published, the messages may not spend
      any time at all waiting in the queue. In this case the priority
      queue will not get any opportunity to prioritise them.
    </p>

    <p>
      In most cases you will want to use the <code>basic.qos</code>
      method in manual acknowledgement mode on your consumers, to
      limit the number of messages that can be out for delivery at any
      time and thus allow messages to be prioritised.
    </p>

    <h2>Interaction with other features</h2>

    <p>
      In general priority queues have all the features of standard
      RabbitMQ queues: they support persistence, paging, mirroring,
      and so on. There are a couple of interactions that should be
      noted though:
    </p>

    <ul>
      <li>
        <a href="ttl.html">Messages which should expire</a> will still
        only expire from the head of the queue. This means that unlike
        with normal queues, even per-queue TTL can lead to expired
        lower-priority messages getting stuck behind non-expired
        higher priority ones. These messages will never be delivered,
        but they will appear in queue statistics.
      </li>
      <li>
        <a href="maxlength.html">Queues which have a max-length
        set</a> will, as usual, drop messages from the head of the
        queue to enforce the limit. This means that higher priority
        messages might be dropped to make way for lower priority ones,
        which might not be what you would expect.
      </li>
    </ul>
  </body>
</html>
