<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xml" href="page.xsl"?>
<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xmlns:doc="http://www.rabbitmq.com/namespaces/ad-hoc/doc">
  <head>
    <title>RabbitMQ - Commercial Services</title>
  </head>
  <body>
    <doc:div>
    <h2>Services</h2>
    <p class="intro">
      RabbitMQ is commercially supported by SpringSource professional services, which includes
      the expertise of RabbitMQ's core team and principal contributors.
    </p>
    <p>
      If you are looking for more background information on RabbitMQ please download this
      <a href="/resources/RabbitMQ_Introduction.pdf">introductory brochure</a>, which contains
      an introduction to RabbitMQ including some documented cases of how others are using RabbitMQ in the wild.</p>

    <h3>RabbitMQ Support</h3>
    <p>
      RabbitMQ support is the best way to assure your system is dependable and to harness the full
      power of the RabbitMQ platform. With RabbitMQ support you will get to access to the best management
      and technical service levels that are available anywhere.</p>
    <p><a href="contact.html">Contact us</a> for more details on RabbitMQ support.</p>

    <h3>RabbitMQ Training</h3>
    <p>
      To accelerate RabbitMQ deployment and product knowledge transfer we offer role-based training courses
      worldwide. These focus on the use cases and patterns for best practice with RabbitMQ and AMQP, as well
      as design, architecture and future development.
    </p>
    <p><a href="contact.html">Contact us</a> for more details on RabbitMQ training.</p>

    <h3>RabbitMQ Expert Consulting</h3>
    <p>
      We offer a full range of consulting services to help developers go from download to deployment and
      beyond. Our team of RabbitMQ experts can help you take your application to the next level of architecture
      and performance. With RabbitMQ consulting services, your infrastructure will remain stable and robust, supporting
      your operations and continuing to deliver value as your business grows.
    </p>
    <p>
      We provide client-driven engagements that focus on knowledge and skills transfer. Our custom professional
      services are highly flexible to address specific issues such as on-site troubleshooting, design review, deployment
      planning, project delivery and other value-adding services tailored to suit your needs. We also provide packaged
      professional services covering architectural application review, migration and solutions and proof of concept.
    </p>
    <p><a href="contact.html">Contact us</a> for more details on RabbitMQ consulting services.</p>

    </doc:div>
  </body>
</html>
