<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xml" href="page.xsl"?>
<html xmlns:doc="http://www.rabbitmq.com/namespaces/ad-hoc/doc">
  <head>
    <title>RabbitMQ - Commercial Services</title>
  </head>
  <body>
    <doc:div>
    <h2>Services</h2>
    
    <p class="intro">Founded by the creators of RabbitMQ, Rabbit Technologies Ltd (RTL) delivers enterprise-class support and services to the hundreds of organisations worldwide that wish to leverage the knowledge and expertise behind RabbitMQ.</p>
    
    <h2>RabbitMQ Support</h2>
    
    <p>RabbitMQ support is the best way to assure your system is dependable and to harness the full power of the RabbitMQ platform. With RabbitMQ support you will get to access to the best management and technical service levels that are available anywhere. </p>
    
    <p><a href="mailto:info@rabbitmq.com?subject=RabbitMQ Support">Contact us for more details on RabbitMQ Support</a></p>
    
    <h2>RabbitMQ Training</h2>
    
    <p>To accelerate RabbitMQ deployment and product knowledge transfer, RTL offers role-based training courses. These focus on the use cases and patterns for best practice with RabbitMQ and AMQP, as well as its design, architecture and future development.
    </p>
    
    <p>In addition to open-enrollment courses and fixed price packages, we provide on-site training worldwide that can be tailored to customers' specific needs.</p>
    <p><a href="mailto:info@rabbitmq.com?subject=RabbitMQ Training">Contact us for more details on RabbitMQ Training</a></p>
    
    <h2>RabbitMQ Consulting Services</h2>
    <p>RTL offers a full range of consulting services to help developers go from download to deployment and beyond. Our team of RabbitMQ experts can help you take your application to the next level of architecture  and performance. With RabbitMQ consulting services, your infrastructure will remain stable and robust, supporting your operations and continuing to deliver value as your business grows.</p>
    
    <p>We provide client-driven engagements that focus on knowledge and skills transfer. Our custom professional services are highly flexible to address specific issues such as on-site troubleshooting, design review, deployment planning, project delivery and other value-adding services tailored to suit your needs. We also provide packaged professional services covering architectural application review, migration and solutions and proof of concept. </p>
    
    <p><a href="mailto:info@rabbitmq.com?subject=RabbitMQ Consulting">Contact us for more details on RabbitMQ Consulting Services</a></p>
    
  <p>For more information you can <a href="http://lists.rabbitmq.com">join our 
  mailing list</a>, or alternatively contact us directly at <a href="
  mailto:info@rabbitmq.com">info@rabbitmq.com</a>. 
  </p>
    </doc:div>
  </body>
</html>
