<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xml" href="page.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE html [
<!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "rabbit.ent" >
%entities;
]>
<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
      xmlns:doc="http://www.rabbitmq.com/namespaces/ad-hoc/doc"
      xmlns:x="http://www.rabbitmq.com/2011/extensions">
  <head>
    <title>Troubleshooting</title>
  </head>
  <body>
        <dl class="instructions">
          <dt><strong>Checking Broker Status</strong></dt>
          <dd>
            <p>
              You can use <code>rabbitmqctl status</code>
              to verify whether a broker is running.<br />
              Normal output from a running broker without plugins follows this pattern:
              <pre>
  Status of node 'rabbit@xxx' ...
  [{pid,...},
   {running_applications,[{rabbit,"RabbitMQ","&version-server;"},
                          {os_mon,"..."},
                          {sasl,"..."},
                          {mnesia,"..."},
                          {stdlib,"..."},
                          {kernel,"..."},
  {os,"..."},
  {erlang_version,"..."},
  {memory,"..."}}]</pre>
            </p>
            <p>
              This example indicates that no broker is running:
              <pre>
  Status of node 'rabbit@xxx' ...
  Error: unable to connect to node 'rabbit@xxx': nodedown
  diagnostics:
  - nodes and their ports on xxx: [{rabbitmqctl,...}]
  - current node: 'rabbitmqctlxxx@xxx'
  - current node home dir: [...]
  - current node cookie hash: [...]</pre>
            </p>
            <p>
              If the diagnostic line looks like this:
              <pre>
  - nodes and their ports on xxx: [{rabbit,...},{rabbitmqctl,...}]</pre>
  and the <a href="relocate.html">broker log file</a> contains entries
  similar to
              <pre>
  Connection attempt from disallowed node...</pre> then you should
  make sure the <a href="clustering.html#setup">erlang cookies</a> are
  the same, e.g. by checking that the cookie hash displayed in the
  diagnostics is the same as that shown by the broker when it starts
  up.
            </p>
            <p>
              A common reason for cookie mismatches when invoking
              rabbitmqctl against a broker on the same host is that
              broker and rabbitmqctl were run as different
              user. Evidence of this comes in the form of a mismatch
              in the node home dir shown by the broker on startup vs
              what is displayed in the rabbitmqctl diagnostics.
            </p>
            <p>
              In the absence of the "<code>Connection attempt from
              disallowed node...</code>" log entry, check that the
              Erlang distribution port on which the broker is
              listening is not blocked by a <a
              href="clustering.html#firewall">firewall</a>. The port
              is shown in the <code>{rabbit,...}</code> part of the
              "<code>nodes and their ports...</code>" diagnostics
              line. Try connecting to it with e.g. telnet.
            </p>
            <p>
              If the "<code>nodes and their ports...</code>" line
              contains no entry for rabbit then the broker probably
              isn't running. Check the broker logs for errors.
            </p>
          </dd>
          <dt><strong>Server Fails to Start</strong></dt>
          <dd>
            <p>
              When the server fails to start, usually a crash dump file
              <code>erl_crash.dump</code> is created in the directory
              where the server was started. This can provide very detailed
              information on the causes of a start up failure, but its
              analysis requires Erlang expertise.
            </p>
            <p>
          If you attempt to start another server while a broker is already running,
          then you will receive an error report.
          You can confirm whether the broker is already running by checking the status.
            </p>
            <p>
              If the server fails to start, examine the console output and
              the log files in the <b>RABBITMQ_LOG_BASE</b> directory.
              Configuration and permission errors are frequently the cause, e.g. the
              Mnesia directory cannot be created.
            </p>
          </dd>
          <dt><strong>Windows Service fails to Install</strong></dt>
          <dd>
            <p>
            If the service fails to install, check the service account has full access permission for
            <b>RABBITMQ_BASE</b>, <b>RABBITMQ_MNESIA_BASE</b> and
            <b>RABBITMQ_LOG_BASE</b> directories
            [<a href="http://www.microsoft.com/windowsxp/using/security/learnmore/accesscontrol.mspx">XP</a>,
                <a href="http://windows.microsoft.com/en-US/windows-vista/Troubleshoot-access-denied-when-opening-files-or-folders">Vista</a>].
            </p>
          </dd>
          <dt><strong>Windows Service fails to Start</strong></dt>
          <dd>
            <p>
            If the service fails to start, make sure the service has been
            installed.
            </p>
            <p>
                On starting the service, if the service output reads "<code>The process
                terminated unexpectedly</code>" instead, then the
                service did not start correctly. Check that the
                environment variables are set correctly. The logfiles in
                <code>RABBITMQ_BASE</code> may also contain useful diagnostic
                information.
            </p>
            <p>
              If <code>RABBITMQ_BASE</code> path contains non-ASCII characters, RabbitMQ service may fail to start
              with the error "<code>RabbitMQ: Erlang machine stopped instantly (distribution name conflict?)</code>". If this is the case,
              override <code>RABBITMQ_BASE</code> to point to a directory that only has ASCII characters and <em>re-install</em> the service
              (restarting will not be sufficient).
            </p>
          </dd>
          <dt><strong>You receive an error message reading "The handle is invalid" after upgrading the Windows Service</strong></dt>
          <dd>
            <p>
            The solution is to uninstall RabbitMQ and Erlang.
            Then remove all registry keys under <code>HKLM/SOFTWARE/Ericsson/Erlang/ErlSrv</code>,
            and then install Erlang and RabbitMQ (in that order).
            </p>
            <p>
            </p>
          </dd>
          <dt><strong>Plugin fails to activate</strong></dt>
          <dd>
            <p>
            If a plugin fails to activate, check the output of
            <code>rabbitmq-plugins list</code>.
            </p>
          </dd>
          <dt><strong>Problems with SSL</strong></dt>
          <dd>
            <p>
              See <a href="troubleshooting-ssl.html">SSL troubleshooting</a>.
            </p>
          </dd>
        </dl>
        <p>
          If the server is not behaving as expected during operation,
          examine the log files and use the <code>rabbitmqctl</code>
          commands from the <a href="admin-guide.html">admin guide</a>
          to obtain further information on the server status.
        </p>
        <p>
          For problems encountered in the handling of AMQP traffic,
          the <a href="api-guide.html#tracer">AMQP capture and analysis
          tool</a> may help in the analysis.
        </p>
        <p>
          Failing that, it's possible that we've solved the problem for someone else.
          Try using the search box at the top of our web pages to find site,
          mailing list and blog information.
           You might also check our
          <a href="http://lists.rabbitmq.com/pipermail/rabbitmq-discuss/">mailing list archives</a>.
        </p>
        <p>
          If you still can't find a solution to your problem then
          please post a new message to
          <a href="mailto:rabbitmq-discuss@lists.rabbitmq.com">rabbitmq-discuss@lists.rabbitmq.com</a>
          (you may have to
          <a href="http://lists.rabbitmq.com/cgi-bin/mailman/listinfo/rabbitmq-discuss">
          join the mailing list first</a>).
          Let us know what you were trying to do, the error you received and
          relevant entries from the logfile and one of our engineers will help you get it fixed.
        </p>
        <p>
          If all of the above fails, please <a href="contact.html">tell us about the problem</a>,
          including the log files under <b>RABBITMQ_LOG_BASE</b> in your report.
        </p>
  </body>
</html>
