<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xml" href="page.xsl"?>
<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xmlns:doc="http://www.rabbitmq.com/namespaces/ad-hoc/doc">
  <head>
    <title>RabbitMQ Dependencies</title>
  </head>
  <body>
    <div>
    <h3>Which Version of Erlang?</h3>
    <p>
    The default version of Erlang provided by your package manager should allow your RabbitMQ server to run,
    and will normally be sufficient.
    In all cases the minimum version required is at least R12B-3. Some functionality provided by erlang requires more recent versions.
    </p>
    <p>
      In general use the latest non-alpha version unless you have a *really* good reason.
    </p>
    <p>
    <table>
      <th>Requirement</th><th>Minimum version</th><th>Notes</th>
      <tr><td>to work at all</td><td>R12B-3</td><td></td></tr>
      <tr><td>build from source</td><td>R12B-5</td><td></td></tr>
      <tr><td>use mochiweb</td><td>R13B01</td><td></td></tr>
      <tr><td>management plugin</td><td>R13B01</td><td>Depends on mochiweb</td></tr>
      <tr><td>work on Windows</td><td>R13B03</td><td></td></tr>
      <tr><td>use SSL reliably</td><td>R14B (SSL 4.0.1)</td><td>Earlier versions do not support SSL well</td></tr>
    </table>
    </p>
    <p>
      <a href="http://www.erlang.org/download.html">Download</a> or check on a specific version of <a href="http://www.erlang.org">Erlang</a>.
    </p>
    <h3>Using a newer version of Erlang than the distribution repository provides</h3>
   
    <p>
    <dl>
    <dt>RedHat Enterprise Linux (RHEL) 5 and derived distributions (e.g. CentOS 5):</dt>
    <dd>
    <p>
    Due to
    <a href="http://fedoraproject.org/wiki/EPEL/GuidelinesAndPolicies">
    the EPEL package update policy</a>,
    EPEL 5 contains Erlang version R12B-5, which rabbitmq-server still supports.
    </p>
    <p>For better performance, and for certain non-core features
    (SSL support, HTTP-based plugins), use the most recent stable version of Erlang.
    The owner of the EPEL erlang package provides a package repository:
    (as root)
    <code> wget -O /etc/yum.repos.d/epel-erlang.repo 
    http://repos.fedorapeople.org/repos/peter/erlang/epel-erlang.repo</code>.

    Invoking <code>yum install erlang</code> will then install or update Erlang.
    </p>
    </dd>
    <dt>Update the distribution</dt>
    <dd>
    If you need newer features of Erlang than the package manager for your Linux distribution provides,
    the best course may be to update your distribution.
    </dd>
    <dt>Building Erlang from source</dt>
    <dd>
     <p>
    Be aware that if building Erlang from source, the package manager can't know
    whether the dependency is already available.
    So, for example, if you install an <a href="http://rpm.org/">rpm</a> package,
    you will get a dependency error. Mixing source builds with packages should be avoided.
    </p>
    </dd>
    </dl>
    </p>

    </div>
  </body>
</html>
